<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bryantduong.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://bryantduong.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-10T14:26:30+00:00</updated><id>https://bryantduong.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Bryant Duong - Personal Portfolio </subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Career Journey Story, Academic Research, and How to get Involved</title><link href="https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2024/manifesto/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Career Journey Story, Academic Research, and How to get Involved"/><published>2024-10-23T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-23T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2024/manifesto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2024/manifesto/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="a-note-to-the-reader">A Note to the Reader</h1> <p>As a student writing this currently applying to PhD programs in Computational Biology, I realized that my situation was unique in that I came from a background with no prior undergraduate research experience and went to industry before I decided to explore academic research. This blog post serves as a small piece of advice in hopes that the reader gains a new perspective or a new resource they didn’t know about prior. I’m also currently writing my admissions essays right now, and felt like this would be a good break to reflect and figure out how to present the timeline of how I got into research and the research questions I want to answer later on.</p> <p>Again, this is my personal view of research and my own opinions of topics that are already probably covered by advice lists such as Tao Xie’s <a href="https://taoxie.cs.illinois.edu/advice.htm">advice list</a> which is also in my bookmarks I will share below. If you want to <strong>skip</strong> my career story (understandable as I wrote a lot), scroll down to <a href="#getting-into-a-lab">Getting into a Lab</a>!</p> <h1 id="background-story">Background Story</h1> <h2 id="industry">Industry</h2> <p>I have been a software engineer in the healthcare industry since 2019, when I graduated from undergrad. As someone with no Computer Science degree, I took MOOC’s from EdX to supplement my coding background. When I joined UnitedHealth, I was part of our Technology Development program, which had two six-month rotations on different teams across different departments. My first rotation was related to Data Science in a chaotic team who wanted to pursue machine learning in the Community &amp; State department. Community &amp; State deals with government programs such as Medicare, Medicaid, and Long-Term care/retirement insurance claims as well as their electronic health records which record patient data. With so much clinical and insurance data provided to me, albeit messy and disorganized on legacy Oracle databases, I took it upon myself to find a use case in a software engineering team. I ended up creating two applications which are used in a different form now to email parse Oracle reports for query remediation. This identifies queries from users across our company that may be inefficient and degrade performance on the production databases.</p> <p>This involved a lot of messy regex and text parsing, and I ended up learning a lot about new things online courses and school do not teach you well. For example, using the Terminal <strong>very</strong> well and shortly learning that projects can be scrapped at any notice if you do not have anyone backing you. I had plenty of ideas, and like research, if you do not sell these ideas for a grant, your ideas go nowhere. My Oracle report parser might have been rather dull and not flashy in any shape or form, but I loved the idea of reducing technical debt and time waste.</p> <p>This led me to my second project in my first rotation which was using STIN transactions and tracking them to see where database imports were lagging to inform engineers and database admins on how to troubleshoot. Although this got farther than my Oracle reporting and was more flashy since I made a dashboard, it wasn’t used because a lot of people didn’t have any prior knowledge in STIN data in the first place. This leads me to my takeaways.</p> <h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2> <ul> <li>Innovation may make sense to you as a developer, but not necessarily to stakeholders you may try to appeal to.</li> <li>Scrapped projects may have logic or learning lessons you can use and recycle. I had six projects not gain any traction or funding until I made a big hit.</li> <li>Mentoring people is the best way to learn. It is <em>selfless</em> work but you end up having to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging">rubber ducky</a> processes and explain how you arrive to conclusions, especially to trainees. This helped me build up soft skills like presentations and documentation, in addition to debugging and deploying your ideas to production using a sound pipeline.</li> <li>Testing your code and packaging it is an invaluable skill that may not be tested in research. In industry, no one will take your package or application seriously if they cannot replicate it. This is similar to the tenant of reproducible research.</li> <li>This is my first job, and I found myself trying to escape the mentality of treating this as something to overly excel at and prioritizing my work-life balance/health.</li> </ul> <h1 id="getting-into-research---2-years-as-a-mid-and-senior-level-engineer--nih-opportunities">Getting into Research - 2 years as a Mid and Senior Level Engineer + NIH opportunities</h1> <p>After my rotations, I decided to stay on my second team (some variation post re-org exists today that I am on) which was an application/full-stack development team. This team had more direction and freedom to explore new ideas as an innovation team. It was still under the department that focused on government funded health insurance, and had way more data than its commercial counterpart. I ended up adopting open-source software by the Apache Foundation which creates a lot of data-driven pipeline projects as part of their incubation project efforts to our use cases. Taking advantage of Apache software and learning to refactor aspects of it to work on our on-premise cloud architecture taught me a lot about DevOps and deployments as well as providing technical support to applications.</p> <p>I wanted to gain more leadership experience by architecting solutions and involving myself in product management. As a result, the company helped support me in getting an MBA at UC Davis, which was my first online program during the pandemic. I enjoyed how I made friends from my very first course (and we still are to this day) and I learned that graduate school is more mature/professional oriented. It was here that I learned how I learned and how to make friends/network to make sustained relationships in my career as well. After this, I began reading about graduate school for Computer Science and bridge programs to brush up on Computer Science theory. I then applied to CS bridge-like programs, including MCIT at Penn.</p> <p>I used this as a stepping stone to get a foundation as well as take advantage of my status as a Master’s student. I wanted to explore what else I could do adjacent in academia relating to EHRs and clinical data. After two months of looking for something, I found some programs to apply to that had summer experiences. The reasoning behind this was the following:</p> <ul> <li>I had only taken up to 594, and had practical scripting experience. I wanted 596 under my belt before I explored research with faculty because that would give some mathematical familiarity + knowledge on algorithms.</li> <li>I wanted some prior experience to prove I could handle a lab to myself and see if I wanted to do research.</li> </ul> <p>I ended up getting accepted to the Graduate Data Science Summer Program at the National Institutes of Health (NIH). It was a cohort of 13 other students in graduate programs who wanted to get involved in technical problems in academic research which was a great stepping stone. The NIH is a government institute that provides a bunch of resources in terms of student training. Every day, there was some workshop, guest speaker, or networking event you could attend if you wanted. If you want to read more about the research I was involved in, you can find my project post <a href="https://bryantduong.github.io/projects/3_project/">here</a>. I took advantage of a lot of events such as talks by guest speakers and workshops throughout my summer, and I enjoyed every second of it.</p> <h2 id="takeaways-1">Takeaways</h2> <ul> <li>Its never too late to do research, especially if you have experience in industry. In fact, years of experience at a company can help inform you on soft skills that students may not have that have no prior professional experience</li> <li>Similar to jobs, apply like you mean it. Apply, apply, apply and do not fear being ghosted or rejection. Its all part of the process, and if you’re serious about pursuing a research experience - whether you want a PhD or to try it out, you have to put some effort into it.</li> <li>Professional Masters students especially in online programs may find it harder to search for opportunities. Students in professional programs typically do not pursue research and their main goal is finding a job in industry. It will be hard to find students with the same goals as you, but there are also many online communities you can probably read posts from. Subreddits like r/labrats, r/GradSchool and r/PhD helped me a lot with this and imposter syndrome.</li> <li>Being humble and asking questions without the fear of feeling stupid helps a lot. Even if I am behind my peers in Biology knowledge, I can’t change that and I take everything as a learning experience. In fact, I probably ask some common sense no-brainers on foundational topics, but its for my own benefit.</li> <li>Attend everything (including conferences) and anything when you do get an opportunity. Its good to get a lot of experiences, but the effort you put in will result in a better summer experience or lab experience.</li> <li>Infrastructure is <em>100%</em> different in research. Research uses a lot of high performance computing clusters fitted with GPU units using their own homebrew linux commands such as Slurm to deploy batch versus just Cloud technologies like Azure Stack pipelines. Linux shell scripting and knowing bash is very translatable and helpful, however.</li> <li>Balancing a remote industry job while taking 593 AND doing research definitely burned me out some nights, but this was worth it due to personal circumstances.</li> </ul> <h1 id="getting-into-a-lab">Getting into a Lab</h1> <p>After summer, I found working in research was more fulfilling due to the complexity of problems while also still having the freedom to explore niche questions that I loved at UHG on the innovation team. I was in my Fall 2023 semester taking 594 + 595, and wanted to get involved with faculty and join a lab after my NIH research experience. I started to contact assistant faculty in various STEM disciplines who did applied computational research because one of my friends I made at the NIH suggested that assistant faculty may be easier to approach, with a new lab and more eager to hire students + give hands-on mentorship. I found this to be the case when I joined my current lab and cold emailed my advisor. She wanted me to move to Philadelphia to work and also contact the lab members to see if I was a good fit, which I was completely fine with and did for the summer at NIH (all of course, thanks to my understanding managers at UHG and remote nature of my job). This felt more like getting to know the people I was working with rather than the typical technical interview I was used to and a bit of a relief. After I got to learn a bit about everyone I started getting into research and joining the lab mid-December 2023 and have worked on projects here since!</p> <h1 id="advice-and-takeaways---in-no-particular-order">Advice and Takeaways - In No Particular Order</h1> <ul> <li>Cold emails like summer research experiences can get a bunch of varied responses including none…at all.</li> <li>Read the faculty’s personal website to determine fit and from there, a recent publication by the lab. Some faculty have a section specifically about what you should include in your email to join their lab.</li> <li>Make sure you balance your other priorities so that you can fully commit to research projects.</li> <li>Time commitment should be communicated at the start with your advisor and a clear career goal/path to your goals should be defined well. <ul> <li>Some of the meetings I have with my advisor are purely career advice and giving an update into my life.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Read a lot of papers, even if you do not understand anything.</li> <li>Advice on <a href="http://linyun.info/p83-keshavA.pdf">how to read a paper</a>.</li> <li>Do not be afraid to present scientific work to your lab or at conferences, even if you sound stupid or can’t answer questions. Its a learning process and I still feel the imposter syndrome every day. Even if I freeze up on presenting, its because I’m learning to interpret science and getting used to the format.</li> <li>Not all publications are weighed equally. Some are in more prestigous journals depending on the discipline and “tiered” differently - this can reflect the rigor of the review process and you need to temper your expectations. Some journals have “sub-journals” which have different tiers from their parent journals. Check its impact factor to learn more.</li> <li>Here are my Chrome <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1-gS2JovppZvyC3t-RdWSWA69MbQ4ePiV/view?usp=sharing">bookmarks</a> you can import that will give you research links I used to find summer and year-round experiences outside of Penn.</li> <li>PhD admissions require some time to be successful (still to be determined for me!) - spend at least 3 months before the deadline gathering application materials and shortlisting schools/recommenders. Most programs have deadlines in December of that year for admission into the following year.</li> <li>You will perpetually feel like you have no idea what you are doing, but that’s because research is open-ended.</li> <li>You have to convince yourself that you want to pursue research if it ends up being your goal long-term, as the ROI on industry is definitely higher than research. I recommend this <a href="https://www.cs.cmu.edu/~harchol/gradschooltalk.pdf">document</a> to go down the rabbit hole of motivations behind a PhD.</li> <li>Someone sent me a <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/15-oQKkuU-CDmzKcK1FT56GuK1V8KCcfG/view?usp=sharing">story</a> of someone else’s PhD journey. Its a great story and was in part a factor of motivation for me to pursue research.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academia"/><category term="research"/><category term="advice"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Getting involved in academic research with industry experience and my career journey]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Reflection on Mentorship</title><link href="https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2024/mentorship/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Reflection on Mentorship"/><published>2024-03-11T12:04:12+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-11T12:04:12+00:00</updated><id>https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2024/mentorship</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2024/mentorship/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="a-note-to-the-reader">A Note to the Reader</h1> <p>I am writing this as a shorter reflection of unordered miscellaneous learnings and lessons over the years on mentorship - technical and non-technical.</p> <h2 id="being-a-great-mentee">Being a Great Mentee</h2> <p>Being a great mentee is honestly harder in my opinion than being a mentor. Why? Because you hold yourself accountable for what you want out of the experience. Your mentor will not know what your challenges, accomplishments, and learning style will be unless you openly communicate with them. A good mentor will be able to assume personality fit and characteristics about you, but it is ultimately up to you what you get out of the experience. Being a mentee at the NIH and now a research lab has taught me the following:</p> <ul> <li>You can always learn from someone. If you can’t find someone, you either outgrew the environment you’re in or you’re not listening/trying to seek out mentors.</li> <li>There are no dumb questions but there are questions that show that you aren’t listening to your mentor. Ask questions when you think they are dumb but make sure to think them out, and make sure they are thoughtful. Topics shouldn’t be restricted if your mentor is a resource, but repeating what they just said to expected you to know <em>verbatim</em> is not helpful to anyone.</li> <li>Reach out to schedule 1x1 meetings with your mentor on a regular basis</li> <li>Network with your fellow mentees and learn from them about your mentor and their own work to gain different perspectives</li> <li>Give your best effort consistently. We all have our off days, but if someone is putting in effort to mentor you, you should expect to deliver the same.</li> </ul> <h2 id="becoming-a-great-mentor">Becoming a Great Mentor</h2> <p>This list is a bit shorter, as a lot of it is similar to above:</p> <ul> <li>There are no dumb questions only non-serious answers - If your mentee asks something that seems obvious to you, don’t ridicule them. Reflect on why they asked that and how they arrived to that train of thought, unless it something they said they’ve understood in the past or something they can easily follow online. Then refer them to a link with suggested keywords for next time.</li> <li>Take note of your mentees learning style - Is it online? Do they do better with visuals? Are they more introverted and prefer to look at your code? Tailor the experience to them.</li> <li>Don’t be afraid to weave in personal elements. Personally, I think giving my mentees relatable stories whether it be career transition to tech or how I learned in undergrad/high school or how I grew up, helps me feel more relatable and comfortable to the audience.</li> <li>Make sure to give some challenges and not just hand out answers.</li> <li>As your mentee grows, include challenges along the way that are solvable. This can be in the form of presentations or technical problems they need to solve.</li> <li>Learn from your mentee and don’t dismiss approaches you didn’t think of. Mentees should be thought of as your peers. Who knows? One day you may work alongside them. Always treat others the way you wish to be treated.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="personal"/><category term="advice"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflection on mentorship and why your audience matters.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pokemon - 20 Years Later &amp;amp; Catching Them All</title><link href="https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2023/pokemon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pokemon - 20 Years Later &amp;amp; Catching Them All"/><published>2023-12-11T10:23:52+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T10:23:52+00:00</updated><id>https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2023/pokemon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bryantduong.github.io/blog/2023/pokemon/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="primer">Primer</h2> <p>Pokemon is a popular worldwide media franchise, featuring a variety of creatures with different abilities and powers that live alongside humans. The franchise includes video games, animated series, and a trading card game as its main forms of media. Pokemon Emerald on the Gameboy Advance handheld console is one of the most popular and well-known games made in 2005. Since its popular release as one of the third generation Pokemon video games in the series, it has grown to have a dedicated fanbase of streamers revisiting the games to play/speed run it as well as a dedicated community of ROM hackers who try to find exploits and glitches in the game’s machine code as well create modded versions of their own game based on the original game.</p> <h2 id="completing-the-pokedex-and-caveats">Completing the Pokedex and Caveats</h2> <p>One of my earliest goals as a kid growing up playing Pokemon Emerald on the gameboy was to catch every Pokemon in the Pokedex. Researching this now and feeling a bit of nostalgia towards childhood memories, I decided to continue my Pokemon journey to catch them all only using the games at my disposal (no hacking, but glitching allowed). There was only one problem: I would need to acquire all the games. Here’s why.</p> <p>In generation 3 and Pokemon Emerald, this meant catching all 386 Pokemon in the game. Some are locked behind special events where you had to go in-person to retrieve a gift and some were version exclusive. Pokemon Emerald was part of a trio of games in the same generation as well as two remakes of the first generation of games: Pokemon Ruby and Sapphire; Pokemon FireRed and Leaf Green. Emerald was considered to be a combination of Ruby and Sapphire, touting to have most of both of the versions and the best of both worlds.</p> <p>However, Ruby and Sapphire have some exclusives that are not in Emerald and the remakes of the first generation games: Fire Red and Leaf Green also had older pokemon needed to complete the Pokedex. This meant in order to obtain all 386 Pokemon, you would need to go to multiple events that had already passed or get lucky and know someone with some of them as well as own all 5 games in generation 3. In addition to this, some event pokemon were only available in Japan on Japanese Pokemon Emerald cartridges. This meant I also had to obtain a Japanese version of Emerald to get a legit Jirachi event.</p> <p>I was lucky enough to haggle around to find authentic game cartridges for all 5 games (6, if you count Japanese Emerald). A YouTuber named TechnoTrainer also had the same bit of nostalgia and was completing the Pokedex for a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dPoy4KCq1oI">video</a> he made. He discusses how much it costs to obtain these games now as they are considered retro and rare to find in decent condition and how he was offering event pokemon that you could legitimately obtain still if you mailed cartridges to him. I mailed my cartridges in and got some of the exclusive legendary Pokemon that only appeared in events.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/eon_ticket_event.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Visualization of a Hive Table in Amundsen" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> One of the exclusive events TechnoTrainer had physically - the Eon Ticket which allows you to capture Latios/Latias </div> <p>The remaining events that are lost to time would need a more technical, yet known glitching approach which I can explain below.</p> <h2 id="arbitrary-code-execution">Arbitrary Code Execution</h2> <p>The <a href="https://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Pomeg_glitch">Pomeg Glitch</a> uses as in-game item in Emerald called the Pomeg Berry. The Pomeg Berry is an item that when used on a Pokemon lowers its HP stats. If used on a 1 HP pokemon, the Pokemon will glitch out and put the current HP to 0 without causing it to faint or a negative number which is non intended. This can depend on cartridges and your language of the game, but long story short, this allows the Pokemon to become a glitching egg that can execute assembly or machine code (very low/system-level code) using the titles of Pokemon PC boxes where Pokemon outside of your party are stored inside a data structure. The titles of these boxes are then used to execute the code given by characters and ASCII values, thus generating whichever Pokemon event item or action you wish to do in your game. All the caveats of the glitch guide can be found <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=83vuZEBd05s">here</a>.</p> <p>When I have free time, I plan to follow the guide to finish all 5 games and their story modes as well as trade them over into one singular game and complete the Pokedex. More technical aspects such as bootstrap unlocking your game and generating Pokemon per byte can be found <a href="https://e-sh4rk.github.io/ACE3/emerald/getting-started/introduction/">here</a>. Just thought it would be neat to write this all down as this was a game released to the US <strong>20 years ago</strong> and new things are still being found in this game. Its amazing how huge the open source community can be for such a niche.</p> <p>Below is a longer picture of the note Techno sent me for the events!</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/gba_note.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Visualization of a Hive Table in Amundsen" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> He also sent me a cool note saying what events he gave me. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="personal"/><category term="fun"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflecting on the mission of "Gotta Catch 'Em All" in the Gameboy Advance era!]]></summary></entry></feed>